<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Articles on Jonathan Piedra</title>
    <link>http://jpiedra.github.io/article/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Articles on Jonathan Piedra</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2018 21:01:46 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://jpiedra.github.io/article/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>CSS Tip: &#39;overflow-x&#39; for Narrow Contexts</title>
      <link>http://jpiedra.github.io/article/css-tip-overflow-x/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2018 21:01:46 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpiedra.github.io/article/css-tip-overflow-x/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A quick tip that can help handle design cases that include child elements larger than their immediate parent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scripted S3 Site Deployment with AWS CLI and Powershell, Part 2</title>
      <link>http://jpiedra.github.io/article/s3-site-deploy-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2018 13:23:20 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpiedra.github.io/article/s3-site-deploy-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this final post for a two-part series, we&amp;rsquo;ll go over an additional script that can be used to upload all local static site contents to a previously configured Amazon Web Services S3 bucket.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scripted S3 Site Deployment with AWS CLI and Powershell, Part 1</title>
      <link>http://jpiedra.github.io/article/s3-site-deploy-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jan 2018 16:29:20 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpiedra.github.io/article/s3-site-deploy-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Amazon Web Services, through their Simple Storage Service (S3), provide an inexpensive and flexible solution for hosting static websites. These would normally be sites that are developed on a local environment (using &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/overview/quickstart/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://jekyllrb.com/&#34;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;), then pushed to either a web server or - in this case - a cloud-based storage platform configured to make the generated pages public. This post discusses a scripted approach to building a bucket you want to use to host an S3 website from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Connecting to MySQL on a VirtualBox Linux VM</title>
      <link>http://jpiedra.github.io/article/vagrant-mysql/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 21:55:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpiedra.github.io/article/vagrant-mysql/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here are a few considerations to keep in mind if you&amp;rsquo;re running a VirtualBox VM with MySQL on it, and need an application on your host operating system to be able to connect to it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>JavaScript Design Patterns: Module</title>
      <link>http://jpiedra.github.io/article/js-module/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Sep 2017 17:48:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpiedra.github.io/article/js-module/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the second installation of this series on JavaScript design patterns and their implementation, we take a look at the &lt;i&gt;module pattern.&lt;/i&gt; By combining two commonly used features in the language, we can create robust interfaces that hide member variables and methods as we see fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>JavaScript Design Patterns: Constructor</title>
      <link>http://jpiedra.github.io/article/js-constructor/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2017 11:39:57 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpiedra.github.io/article/js-constructor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This first installment in a series discussing various JavaScript design patterns covers one of the most basic patterns available, the &lt;i&gt;constructor pattern.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A simple build script</title>
      <link>http://jpiedra.github.io/article/simple-build-script/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 10:51:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpiedra.github.io/article/simple-build-script/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today we go over the process of writing a very simple Bash script. We&amp;rsquo;ll be able to detect whether a build for a &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/overview/quickstart/&#34;&gt;Hugo static site&lt;/a&gt; is present, push the files to a Git repository for our website, and automate all the steps involved.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Installing squarespace-server on Ubuntu 14.04 LTS</title>
      <link>http://jpiedra.github.io/article/squarespace-server-ubuntu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 18:11:31 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpiedra.github.io/article/squarespace-server-ubuntu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This article details how to install the &lt;a href=&#34;http://developers.squarespace.com/local-development/&#34;&gt;Squarespace local development server&lt;/a&gt; on Ubuntu 14.04 LTS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently took on a small project, some work on customizing Squarespace templates. In the course of doing this, I required the Squarespace local development server in order to quickly modify and test changes to the template. I use a VirtualBox VM I built some time ago using Vagrant, based on Ubuntu 14.04 LTS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve encountered problems installing this program on the aforemention Linux distro, read on and follow these steps, as they ended up working for me very well!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Web API, written using PHP and MySQL - Part 1</title>
      <link>http://jpiedra.github.io/article/php-sql-api-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2017 13:20:54 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jpiedra.github.io/article/php-sql-api-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this first part of a series on implementing a PHP/MySQL-based API endpoint for our data, we go over some basic principles, as well as stated goals, that will guide the work we&amp;rsquo;ll be undertaking later.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>